{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The leader of this event had his followers march to the Sun Inn to demand the release of a group of prisoners. Participants in this event were pardoned by a president who described them as being “as ignorant of our language as they were of our laws.\" A $2 million direct tax to fund the Quasi-War was an immediate cause of this event, during which a group of assessors from Quakertown was targeted. John Adams pardoned the leader of this event, which occurred five years after the similar Whiskey Rebellion. For ten points, what was this 1799 to 1800 farmers’ rebellion in Pennsylvania?",
      "answer": "Fries's Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two years prior to this battle, its victor defeated Murza Begich at the Vorzha River. A number of nobles from Ryazan were possibly killed at this battle, to which Oleg II was crucially late. The kingmaker Mamai led the losing side at this battle and was later killed by Tokhtamysh [[tohk-tah-MISH]]. The victor of this battle was given the epithet “Donskoy\" in reference to a river near this battlefield. For ten points, what 1380 battle was a decisive victory for Dmitri, Prince of Moscow over the Golden Horde?",
      "answer": "Battle of Kulikovo"
    },
    {
      "question": "A governor of this region, named Abdullahi Sadiq [[SAH-deek]], attempted to influence one country to side with the Central Powers of World War One. That leader of this region was a member of the Harari people and forged an alliance with Mohammed Hassan of the Dervish State. A conference in Dire Dawa contributed to disputes over the name of this region, where a raid on an oil facility in Abole [[ah-BOH-leh]] led to a 2007 crackdown by Meles Zenawi’s government. A 1970s war over this region began when Siad Barre’s forces invaded it from the east. For ten points, name this region historically disputed between Somalia and Ethiopia.",
      "answer": [
        "Ogaden",
        "Ogaadeen",
        "Huwan",
        "Soomaali Galbeed"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Person and body part required. This body part is described as being “gaily frilled” in a depiction that shows its owner next to a portrayal of a donkey. The owner of this body part was stationed at Naples prior to a battle in which it was hit by an arquebus shot. The loss of functionality in this body part was said to “bring greater glory” to its right counterpart following its injury at a 1571 victory for Don John of Austria and the Holy League. That injury led this body part's owner to be labelled the “Cripple of Lepanto.” For ten points, name this body part belonging to the author of Don Quixote.",
      "answer": [
        "Cervantes' Arm or Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra’s left arm",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This place's Dau Go cave contains remnants of sharp wooden columns used to sink Mongol ships. This place was the site of the raising of the flag of a provisional government led by Nguyễn Văn Xuân [[WEHN VAHN ZHU-AHN]]. Legends state that the landscape of this area was formed when guardian dragons spat out jewels and jade to protect against invaders, and that Dragon King's seven-day marriage took place in this area's Thien Cung [[TYEN-KUNG]] cave. For ten points, containing over fifteen hundred limestone karst islands, name this arm of the Gulf of Tonkin that was, along with Haiphong Harbor, heavily mined by the U.S. Navy.",
      "answer": [
        "Hạ Long Bay or Halong Bay",
        "or Vịnh Hạ Long"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In one work, this man wrote of studying an “in-between” period of one figure’s life after that figure’s experiences in South Africa. That work by this author is subtitled On the Origins of Militant Nonviolence. A work by this author, originally planned as a chapter about “emotional crises in late adolescence,” tries to explain an exclamation given at a choir practice in Germany. For ten points, name this psychologist and author of Gandhi’s Truth and Young Man Luther who is best known for coining the phrase “identity crisis.”",
      "answer": [
        "Erik Erikson or Erik Homburger Erikson",
        "Erik Salomonsen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1828 poem about one of these people focuses on his relationship with Maria and the revenge of her father, Kochubei. In a novel, one of these people falls in love with Aksinia, who is killed by a stray bullet. The lifestyles of these people in a valley by the title river are depicted in the novel And Quiet Flows the Don. A Tolstoy novel, published in The Russian Messenger, outlines the protagonist's relationship with one of these people named Eroshka who clashes with the Chechens. For ten points, name these people of the Ukrainian steppes, one of whom titles Lord Byron's Mazeppa.",
      "answer": [
        "Cossacks",
        "Don Cossack",
        "Kozak"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Turner family competed with a company named for this early user of direct mail techniques. This man was inspired by a black material found in Italy to name a factory after the region of Etruria. Early in his career, John Flaxman originally worked under this man, who partnered with Thomas Whieldon. For three years, this man tried to replicate the blue and white Portland Vase. This producer of creamware created a medallion depicting a man in chains above the words “Am I Not a Man and a Brother?” For ten points, name this English abolitionist who industrialized pottery production.",
      "answer": [
        "Josiah Wedgwood",
        "Wedgwood pottery",
        "Josiah Wedgwood and Sons Ltd. 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This book's author was present for a scene in this book, where she witnessed the pursuit of the Goeben and Breslau at age two. This book's author cited Thomas Mann, to depict the desires of Germany, in the section \"Flames of Louvain.\" Opening with the funeral of Edward VII [[the Seventh]], this book observes, “On history’s clock it was sunset, and the sun of the old world was setting in a dying blaze of splendor never to be seen again.” Consisting of the sections “Plans,” “Outbreak,” and “Battle,” for ten points, what Barbara Tuchman book detailed the events of the first month of World War One?",
      "answer": "The Guns of August"
    },
    {
      "question": "Journalist Westbrook Pegler wrote an article which claimed this man must be reported to the \"Missing Person's Bureau\" after his RNC presidential nomination. This man's daughter, Nancy Kassebaum, was the first woman ever elected to a full term in the Senate without her husband having previously served in Congress. In one speech, this candidate claimed, \"The price of economic planning is the loss of economic freedom\" in reference to the continuation of FDR's New Deal programs. A landslide loss in the 1936 election was suffered by, for ten points, what Republican candidate and former governor of Kansas?",
      "answer": "Alf Landon or Alfred Mossman Landon 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "220 members of this ethnicity were killed in a disaster involving a ship departing from Cicero. A founder of the Chicago Bears, nicknamed “Papa Bear,” was a member of this ethnicity who was originally thought to have been among the dead on the aforementioned SS Eastland. A mayor of Chicago of this ethnicity was killed during a 1933 attempt on the life of FDR. Members of this ethnic group organized a large rally in Chicago Stadium as the Munich Crisis was unfolding. For ten points, Anton Cermak belonged to what ethnic group, many of whose members came from Bohemia?",
        "answer": [
          "Czech-Americans",
          "Czechoslovakians",
          "natives of the Czech Republic",
          "Czechia",
          "Bohemian Americans before “Bohemia” is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The earlier mentioned “Papa Bear” is what man, whose experiences coaching, playing, and owning a team led him to also be nicknamed “Mr. Everything?”",
        "answer": "George Halas or George Stanley Halas Sr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At a battle in this state, Peter Osterhaus informed Franz Sigel of a knoll that was suitable for artillery, resulting in 21 cannons being placed there to repulse Confederate forces. Carl Van Dorn was the losing commander at that battle in this state sometimes named for Elkhorn Tavern. A deadly firefight arose at Leetown during the aforementioned Battle of Pea Ridge in this state, which was preceded by a march along the Bentonville Detour. That battle in this state occurred near Fayetteville. Washington and Hot Springs both served as Confederate capitals of, for ten points, what Southern state?",
        "answer": "Arkansas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among those wounded at Pea Ridge was a commander at this Missouri battle called the “Gettysburg of the West.”",
        "answer": "Battle of Westport"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Victor Gregg compared this event to being “trapped in a locked cage.” After this event, one man compared the appearance of its central location to Dayton, Ohio and claimed, “There must be a ton of human bone meal in the ground.” Arthur Harris claimed that the target of this event was “a key transportation point.” A mere six Lancasters were shot down during this event that targeted the “Florence of the Elbe.” Kurt Vonnegut wrote about this event in Slaughterhouse-Five. For ten points, name this Allied aerial attack on a German town.",
        "answer": "Bombing of Dresden or Firebombing of Dresden"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What strategic bombers, nicknamed \"Flying Fortresses\" were used for the attack?",
        "answer": "Boeing B-17 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event led nearly 20,000 people in one nation’s capital to protest and to call for the prime minister and his cabinet to resign for failing to prevent this event. Yasushi Nagao won the Pulitzer Prize in 1961 for photographing this event. The person who accomplished this event wrote with toothpaste on the walls of his jail cell, “Would that I had seven lives to give for my country” and “Long live the Emperor\" before committing suicide. Perpetrated by 17-year-old Otoya Yamaguchi, for ten points, what event caused the death of the chairman of the Japan Socialist Party?",
        "answer": [
          "Assassination of Inejirō Asanuma",
          "word forms of \"Assassination\"",
          "descriptive answers like Assassination of the leader of the Socialists in Japan",
          "similar before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Yamaguchi assassinated Asanuma using what weapon, a shorter sword that was wielded by the samurai in feudal Japan?",
        "answer": "Wakizashi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Despite being ethnically Azerbaijani, Mirza Davud Huseynov served the USSR as the first secretary of this present-day nation until his expulsion during the Great Purge. The nationalistic political faction known as the Rastokhez fueled Anti-Armenian riots in this nation put down by the military of Qahhor [[KAH-hohr]] Mahkamov. The title \"Founder Of Peace and National Unity, Leader of the Nation\" is used by this nation's authoritarian leader, Emomali Rahmon, who dominated its politics starting in the mid-1990s. The Dushanbe [[duhr-SHAHN-beh]] Riots occurred in, for ten points, which Central Asian nation?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Tajikstan or Tokjikiston",
          "or Tadzhikistan",
          "or Jumhurii Tojikiston"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The crown on the flag of Tajikistan represents the Samanid Empire, which was originally based in what non-Tajiki ancient city, the former capital of Sogdia?",
        "answer": [
          "Samarkand",
          "Smarkand 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In Jeremiah, a kingdom that shares its name with this person was \"called\" along with Ararat and Minni. John V [[the Fifth]] the Historian claimed that this man’s namesake army was subjugated by a brother who founded the House of Togarmah. This eldest son of Gomer was first associated with a region of Scythia before lending his name to a \"kingdom\" that encompassed the Rhineland. A group named for this man traditionally lives to the east of the Iberian Sephardi community and often speaks Yiddish. For ten points, give this namesake of a group of German Jews.",
        "answer": [
          "Ashkenaz",
          "Ashkenazi",
          "Ashkenazi Jews",
          "Ashkenazaic Jews",
          "Ashkenazim"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Via Japheth, Ashkenaz was the grandson of this other biblical figure. This man once possessed an object that provided a relic to Jacob of Nisibis after a trip to Mount Qardu.",
        "answer": [
          "Noah",
          "Noah's Ark"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The British referred to this vehicle as the Gannett Mark I and received over 1,200 of them via Lend-Lease. This craft's superiority in carrier landings made it a preferable choice compared to the Vought F4U Corvair. David McCampbell was an ace who registered all of his 34 kills in this vehicle. Many participants in the “Great Marianas Turkey Shoot” used these fighters, which saw widespread use in 1943. Intended to counter the Mitsubishi Zero, this vehicle was billed as the “big brother” of the Wildcat. For ten points, name this dominant U.S. fighter during the second half of the Pacific Theatre of World War Two.",
        "answer": [
          "Grumman F6F Hellcat",
          "either underlined portion"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “Great Marianas Turkey Shoot” took place during what 1944 battle that effectively eliminated the Japanese Navy's ability to conduct carrier operations.",
        "answer": "Battle of the Philippine Sea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A composer with this surname, who died of tuberculosis at 24, was the first female winner of the Prix de Rome for composition, for her cantata Faust et Helene. A musician with this surname reportedly memorized the entirety of Bach's Well-Tempered Clavier at just 10 years old. Aaron Copland wrote his Symphony for Organ and Orchestra for a music teacher with this surname who taught over 600 students at the American Conservatory in Fontainebleau. For ten points, give this surname of composer Lili and her sister, Nadia.",
        "answer": "Boulanger"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "It is likely that Lili Boulanger composed a setting for one of these texts in reaction to World War One. Igor Stravinsky wrote a choral symphony to celebrate the 50th anniversary of the Boston Symphony Orchestra titled for these texts, known in Hebrew as Tehillim.",
        "answer": [
          "Book of Psalms",
          "Psalter",
          "Symphony of Psalms",
          "\"Psalm 130\""
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The 154th episode of Top Gear focuses on the hosts' attempt to do this task. One man who attempted to complete this task, with the help of James Grant, died in what may have been a suicide the day before a scheduled debate about that attempt. Richard Burton was a rival of the aforementioned man, who claimed to have done this task shortly after Lake Tanganyika was discovered. John Hanning Speke claimed to have accomplished this task, which David Livingstone later attempted. For ten points, name this task of locating a place, the location of which is still debated today.",
        "answer": "Finding the Source of the Nile River"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Richard Burton was also known for his widely read 1885 translation of this literary work.",
        "answer": [
          "One Thousand and One Nights",
          "The Arabian Nights",
          "The Book of the Thousand Nights and a Night: A Plain and Literal Translation of the Arabian Nights Entertainment",
          "The Arabian Nights' Entertainment 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Inspiring a figure in the Canturbury Tales, this man's knight, Nicholas Colfox, strangled former advisor Thomas of Woodstock. This monarch demolished Sheen Manor following the plague death of his wife, Anne of Bohemia. This ruler, whose reign began with a regency council led by John of Gaunt, was opposed by the \"Merciless Parliament,\" which aimed to halt this man's attempts to make peace during the One Hundred Years' War. A clash between the Yorks and the Lancasters was caused by the deposition of, for ten points, which 14th century Plantagenet king?",
        "answer": [
          "Richard II",
          "Richard of Bordeaux"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which son of John of Gaunt deposed Richard II and later dealt with the revolt of Owen Glendower?",
        "answer": [
          "Henry IV",
          "Henry Bolingbroke"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "the...",
      "prompt": "Name the the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Party which he represented in the presidential elections of 1896, 1900, and 1908.",
          "answer": "Democratic Party or Democrats"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ohio politician who defeated him in the general election twice using the \"Front Porch\" strategy.",
          "answer": "William McKinley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Left-wing agrarian party that supported him through many of his presidential runs.",
          "answer": [
            "Populist Party or Populists",
            "People's Party"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pro-Silver speech he gave which claimed, \"You shall not crucify mankind upon [this title object].\"",
          "answer": "\"Cross of Gold\" Speech"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trial where he claimed Darwinism was a hypothesis while arguing against Clarence Darrow.",
          "answer": [
            "Scopes Monkey Trial",
            "either underlined portion",
            "The State of Tennessee v. John Thomas Scopes"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Midwestern author who followed him on the 1896 campaign trail while working for the Lincoln Courier.",
          "answer": [
            "Willa Cather",
            "Wilella Sibert Cather"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nebraska newspaper he owned and edited, the name of which was a play on his nickname.",
          "answer": [
            "The Commoner",
            "\"The Great Commoner\""
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Oklahoma Governor whose acceptance of bribes from Standard Oil and close ties to Bryan hurt his 1908 Presidential bid",
          "answer": "Charles Nathaniel Haskell 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Suez Crisis",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Suez Crisis, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Middle Eastern power who nationalized the canal, starting the period of tension.",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pan-Arab politician who nationalized the Suez Canal, sparking the crisis.",
          "answer": "Gamal Abdel Nasser Hussein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister of Israel who was advised to attack Egypt at the behest of his high command.",
          "answer": "David Ben-Gurion"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Strip\" of land occupied by Israel along with the Sinai Peninsula during the crisis.",
          "answer": "Gaza Strip"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister of the UK whose administration collapsed following the bungling of the Suez Crisis",
          "answer": "Sir Anthony Eden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future Canadian Prime Minister who won a Nobel Peace Prize while a diplomat for negotiating an end to the Suez Crisis",
          "answer": "Lester B. Pearson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Partially executed Anglo-French operation to seize the Suez Canal zone while Israel invaded the Sinai peninsula",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Muskateer",
            "Operation Muskateer Revised"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French General during the Suez Crisis who later launched a pro-De Gaulle and anti- Fourth Republic coup on Corsica",
          "answer": "Jacques Massu 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Sassanids",
      "prompt": "Concerning Sassanid Persia, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Dualistic Iranian faith which served as their official religion.",
          "answer": [
            "Zoroastrianism",
            "Mazdayasna"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal title held by their rulers.",
          "answer": [
            "Shah",
            "Shahanshah",
            "or Padishah"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First Rashidun caliph who undertook several invasions of the empire and its rival, Eastern Rome.",
          "answer": "Abu Bakr"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of a Gnostic faith who was imprisoned by Bahram I, who denounced his works such as Arzhang.",
          "answer": [
            "Mani",
            "Manichaeism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Great\" king who wrestled Armenia from Rome and repelled an invasion by Julian the Apostate.",
          "answer": [
            "Shapur the Great",
            "Shapur II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman emperor who was captured at Edessa and turned into a footstool.",
          "answer": [
            "Valerian",
            "Publius Licinius Valerianus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nomadic people sometimes known as \"White Huns\" who captured and ransomed King Peroz I.",
          "answer": "Hephthalites"
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal standard of Persia used until the end of the dynasty.",
          "answer": "Derafsh Kaviani 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Clarence DeLaney was a co-founder of this company, one of whose earliest clients was Schlitz. Though not Google, employees of this company were referred to as “Androids” of its founder. David Duncan was a partner at this organization who worked with a client that adopted the “mark-to-market” (20 pts)",
        "method of one practice. That client of this company was led by Jeffrey Skilling. Accenture branched off from this company, which was formerly a member of the Big Five along with Ernst and Young and Deloitte until it became (10 pts)",
        "embroiled in a 2001 scandal. For ten points, name this former accounting firm for Enron."
      ],
      "answer": "Arthur Andersen LLP"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roger of Torre Maggiore wrote a “Sorrowful Lament” focusing on this military campaign, during which one side annihilated the crossbowmen under Count Simon. A preemptive bridge attack during this campaign was partly overseen by a Duke of Slavonia named Coloman. (20 pts)",
        "Gunpowder may have been employed during this campaign, in which Esztergom was besieged following the defeat of Bela IV. The Battle of Mohi was fought during this campaign, in which one side was led by (10 pts)",
        "Batu. For ten points, name this campaign in which a Central Asian empire expanded into Magyar territory."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mongolic invasion of the Kingdom of Hungary",
        "clear knowledge equivalents in place of “invasion”",
        "First",
        "Second Mongol invasion of Hungary"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this conflict, the forces of Henri II Montmorency led a charge across a ditch at the Battle of Veillane. Ambrogio Spinola died of ill health during a siege in this war. The fortress of Casale was besieged twice during this conflict, in which Pinerolo, (20 pts)",
        "and other land taken by France, was renounced in the Treaty of Cherasco. A Piedmont Campaign was carried out during this war, which was precipitated by the deaths of Francesco IV and two other brothers of the House of (10 pts)",
        "Gonzaga. For ten points, name this war which was fought over the throne of a duchy in Italy."
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Mantuan Succession"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's refusal to join a financial house earned him the nickname \"The Lone Wolf of Wall Street.\" This man became the first chairman of the War Industries Board, which managed the United States's mobilization during World War One. At a meeting of the UN Atomic (20 pts)",
        "Energy Commission, this man presented a modified version of the Acheson–Lilienthal Report which was rejected by the Soviet Union. This coiner of the term \"Cold (10 pts)",
        "War\" served as a close advisor to FDR on war supply. For ten points, name this financier whose namesake \"Plan\" was an effort to prevent the spread of nuclear weapons."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bernard Baruch or Bernard Mannes Baruch",
        "Baruch Plan 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Allen Walton founded a company in Hummelstown that was centered around this material. In the late 19th century, a popular variant of this material made Basswood Island in Wisconsin famous. The Clinton Hill and Park Slope (20 pts)",
        "Historic Districts are notable for the prevalence of this material. The ease with which it was carved led to the popularity of this material in the late-Victorian era in Brooklyn, (10 pts)",
        "Harlem, and on the Upper West Side of Manhattan. For ten points, townhouses across New York are known for their use of what Jurassic sandstone?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Brownstone",
        "Hummelstown Brownstone",
        "Bass Island Brownstone Company"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The largest church of this spiritual movement, Unity, was founded by Charles and Myrtle Filmore in 1889. Emma Curtis Hopkins, a leader in this spiritual movement, was referred to as the “Teacher of Teachers.” In his book, The Varieties of Religious Experience, (20 pts)",
        "William James brands this spiritual philosophy as a “Mind-cure movement.” The founder of Christian Science, Mary Baker Eddy, denied that she was inspired by her time as a student of the (10 pts)",
        "founder of this movement. For ten points, the foundations of what spiritual movement were laid by mesmerist Phineas P. Quimby?"
      ],
      "answer": "New Thought movement or Higher Thought"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) 15th century historian Mustafa Ali justified this system by writing, \"War captives constituted as captured loot, and thus was allowed under sharia.\" Ahmet III formally abolished this system following a series of insurrections from its beneficiaries. (20 pts)",
        "This system, from which Jewish and Roma people were exempt due to being \"Protected nations,\" was created by Murad I to counteract the influence of Turkish (10 pts)",
        "nobles with Western vassal-soldiers. The Ottomans utilized, for ten points, what method of child levies on Christian subjects to populate their Janissary Corps?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Devshirme",
        "Devşirme"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Plutarch pairs this historical figure with the orator and general Alcibiades [[al- sih-BYE-ah-dees]] in his work, Parallel Lives. The first speech given by this man was a wordless display of his battle scars to the Roman public. This man was put to death by his enemy-turned-ally-turned-enemy again, Attius (20 pts)",
        "Tullius, after this man's mother, Veturia, begged him not to sack his hometown. A (10 pts)",
        "Shakespearian tragedy is named for, for ten points, what semi-legendary hero of the Early Roman Republic who was exiled from Rome following his defeat of the Volsci [[VOHL-skee]]?"
      ],
      "answer": "Gnaeus Marcius Coriolanus 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On this island, a free black carpenter used a book of images of Haitian leaders to inspire support for his failed slave uprising, the Aponte Revolt. This island’s capital was occupied after a 1762 siege where British troops captured the Morro fort, which broke the (20 pts)",
        "asiento monopoly on this island’s slave trade. This island’s production of one cash crop boomed in response to the Haitian Revolution, from which many refugees fled across the Windward Passage to this island and settled around Baracoa, its first colonial settlement. (10 pts)",
        "Sugar planters led the Ten Years War for independence from Spain in, for ten points, what Caribbean island, whose capital is Havana?"
      ],
      "answer": "Cuba"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alejandro Lanusse contrasts this event with one on October 17, 1945 that involved “the masses imposing their will.\" Jorge Osinde hired a group of 300 men who took part in this event despite being tasked with defending a target of it. Hector Campora (20 pts)",
        "was present at this event, which occurred amid a gathering of over three million people witnessing the return of a leader from an (10 pts)",
        "eighteen-year exile in Spain. Taking place near a namesake airport, for ten points, what was this 1973 attack in which snipers fired into a crowd of Juan Perón supporters in Buenos Aires?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ezeiza Massacre 2021-22 HS National History Bowl - 2021-11-30"
    }
  ]
}